Guide to the Socialist Assemblymen Papers TAM.056.008
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Socialist Assemblymen Papers
1920
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Socialist Party (U.S.)
TAM.056.008
1 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
In 1920, five Socialist Party Assemblymen were expelled from the New York State Assembly on the grounds that membership in the Socialist Party constituted disloyalty to the United States. This collection consists of several documents and numerous supporting letters, all related to the unsuccessful campaign to reverse the expulsion. Note: this collection has been microfilmed, and researchers must use the microfilm copy (R-7124, reel 12).
Custodial History
Transferred from the Rand School Archives, 1962. The accession number associated with this collection is 1962.014.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
During the infamous Red Scare of 1920, five Socialist Party Assemblymen were expelled from the New York State Assembly on the grounds that membership in the Socialist Party constituted disloyalty to the United States. These assemblymen (August Claessens, Samuel A. De Witt, Samuel Orr, Charles Solomon, and Louis Waldman), in conjunction with the Socialist Party, attempted to overturn the Assembly action and be seated as duly elected representatives of their respective assembly districts. To assist the assemblymen in their fight, the Socialist Party organized a special committee for the purpose of raising funds and holding meetings on the case. The New York State Bar Association also appointed a special committee composed of Charles Evans Hughes, Ogden Mills, and Joseph Proskauer to plead for the seating of the assemblymen. These efforts were unsuccessful, however, as the State Assembly refused to reverse its earlier decision.
Scope and Content Note
The Socialist Assemblymen Papers, 1920, consist of four items relating to the expulsion of the assemblymen and numerous contribution letters sent to the Socialist Party committee which administered the assemblymen's defense fund. The four items pertaining to the expulsion of the assemblymen (VIII:1 VIII:4) include a resolution by the New York State Assembly, a statement on the Assembly's action by the New York State Executive Committee of the Socialist Party, a resolution against the Assembly's action by the New York City Board of Aldermen, and a legal brief prepared by the special committee of the New York State Bar Association.
The contribution letters follow these four items in the filming order. These letters are arranged in alphabetical order according to the author of the letter or the organization for which the letter was written. In some instances, each letter of the alphabet has been assigned a frame number. For the most part, however, the letters have been clustered in alphabetical groups, with anonymous letters placed at the end of the collection. These groups of letters have also been assigned frame numbers. Citations for each of the first four items and the contribution letters can be found in the complete reel list for this collection.
The researcher should also note that an error was made in the targeting for this collection. On each frame, the word "Series" appears adjacent to the frame number. This term should actually be interpreted as "Collection".
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into 2 series:
Missing Title
Series I. Papers
Series II. Fragile Originals
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Socialist collections in the Tamiment Library, 1872-1956: a guide to the microfilm edition (Sanford, N.C.: Microfilming Corp. of America, c1979), 181 p.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Due to the fragile nature of the original materials, researchers must use the microfilmed version; microfilm call number is Film R-7124, Reel 12.
Socialists -- United States.; Correspondence.; Official reports.; New York (N.Y.); Memorandums.; Resolutions (administrative records); New York (N.Y.) |x Politics and government |y 1898-1951.; Proskauer, Joseph M. (Joseph Meyer), 1877-1971; Orr, Samuel, 1890-; New York (State). Legislature. Assembly; Mills, Ogden, 1856-1929; Hughes, Charles Evans, 1862-1948; De Witt, S. A. (Samuel Aaron), 1891-; Solomon, Charles; Claessens, August, 1885-1954; Waldman, Louis, b. 1892
- Papers
  - Resolution on the Socialist Assemblymen by the State Assembly, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    Film R-7124, Reel 12: Frame VIII:1
  - Statement on the Assembly Action by the State Executive Committee of the Socialist Party, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Film R-7124, Reel 12: Frame VIII:2
  - Resolution Against the Assembly Action by the Board of Aldermen of the City of New York, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Film R-7124, Reel 12: Frame VIII:3
  - Assembly Judiciary Committee: In The Matter of Louis Waldman, August Claessens, Samuel A. DeWitt, Samuel Orr, and Charles Solomon. Brief of Special Committee Appointed by the Association of the Bar of the City of New York, Jan 20, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Film R-7124, Reel 12: Frame VIII:4
  - Contribution Correspondence, A, 1919-1920 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Film R-7124, Reel 12: Frame VIII:5
  - Contribution Correspondence, B, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Film R-7124, Reel 12: Frame VIII:6
  - Contribution Correspondence, C, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Film R-7124, Reel 12: Frame VIII:7
  - Contribution Correspondence, D-F, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Film R-7124, Reel 12: Frame VIII:8
  - Contribution Correspondence, G-H, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Film R-7124, Reel 12: Frame VIII:9
  - Contribution Correspondence, I-J, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Film R-7124, Reel 12: Frame VIII:10
  - Contribution Correspondence, K-L, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Film R-7124, Reel 12: Frame VIII:11
  - Contribution Correspondence, M, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Film R-7124, Reel 12: Frame VIII:12
  - Contribution Correspondence, N-P, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Film R-7124, Reel 12: Frame VIII:13
  - Contribution Correspondence, R, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Film R-7124, Reel 12: Frame VIII:14
  - Contribution Correspondence, Soc-Swe, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Film R-7124, Reel 12: Frame VIII:16
  - Contribution Correspondence, T-V, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Film R-7124, Reel 12: Frame VIII:17
  - Contribution Correspondence, Wag-Wor, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Film R-7124, Reel 12: Frame VIII:18
  - Contribution Correspondence, Wor-Wry, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Film R-7124, Reel 12: Frame VIII:19
  - Contribution Correspondence, Y-Z, anonymous, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Film R-7124, Reel 12: Frame VIII:20
    - Contribution Correspondence, Sac-Sno, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Film R-7124, Reel 12: Frame VIII:15
- Fragile Originals
  - Fragile Originals from Box 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 2 (Box 3, Folder 2)